<!--Written by Luke Kortepeter June 2013-->
<?xml-model href="http://seward.lib.rochester.edu/tei/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://seward.lib.rochester.edu/sites/default/files/TEI-Boilerplate/content/teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Seward Family Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp ref="Transcriber"/>
               <persName ref="spp:"/>
               <!--Enter three-letter transcriber ID here "ref="spp:zzz"--></respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp ref="Student Editor"/>
               <persName ref="spp:"/>
               <!--Enter three-letter student editor ID here "ref="spp:zzz"--></respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>Seward Family Digital Archive</distributor>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <institution>University of Rochester</institution>
                  <repository>Rare Books and Special Collections</repository>
                  <collection/>
                  <!--Include Collection Name: "Seward Family Papers," "William H. Seward Public Papers," "Grier Papers," "Chesebro Papers," "Miller Papers"--><idno/>
                  <!--Include File Drawer or Box Number, Digital File???--><msName/>
                  <!-- Include ... --></msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <figure n="1"><!--Add page number of letter here--><graphic url="http://seward.lib.rochester.edu/tei/web_letters/titleofLetter/titleOfLetter.jpg"/>
                        <!--Add url to jpeg file of scanned letter--></figure>
                     <figure n="2"><!--Add page number of letter here--><graphic url="http://seward.lib.rochester.edu/tei/web_letters/titleofLetter/titleOfLetter.jpg"/>
                        <!--Add url to jpeg file of scanned letter--></figure>
                     <figure n="3"><!--Add page number of letter here--><graphic url="http://seward.lib.rochester.edu/tei/web_letters/titleofLetter/titleOfLetter.jpg"/>
                        <!--Add url to jpeg file of scanned letter--></figure>
                     <figure n="4"><!--Add page number of letter here--><graphic url="http://seward.lib.rochester.edu/tei/web_letters/titleofLetter/titleOfLetter.jpg"/>
                        <!--Add url to jpeg file of scanned letter--></figure>
                     <!--Add any additional pages here--></additions>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <date when="1830-01-01"/>
                     <!-- Include date in yyyy-mm-dd w/ certainty att. if not 100% --></origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="psn" matchPattern="([a-z]+)" replacementPattern="http://seward.lib.rochester.edu/tei/persons.xml#$1">
               <p> In the context of this project, private URIs with the prefix
                                "psn" point to <gi>person</gi> elements in the project's
                                personography.xml file.
                            </p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="superscript" n="teibp:superscript" scheme="css"> verical-align:
                            super; font-size: 12px; </rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="underline" n="teibp:underline" scheme="css"> text-decoration:
                            underline; </rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="strikethrough" n="teibp:strikethrough" scheme="css"> text-decoration:
                            line-through; </rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="red" n="teibp:red" scheme="css"> color: red; </rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <address>
               <persName xml:id="blah1"/>
               <!-- Include valid person name of sender: "xml:id=SEWf_828"--><placeName xml:id="blah2"/>
               <!--Include valid place name: "xml:id=ALB_1318" or "unknown" for either.--></address>
            <address>
               <persName xml:id="blah3"/>
               <!-- Include valid person name of sender: "xml:id=SEWw_829"--><placeName xml:id="blah4"/>
               <!-- Include valid place name: "xml:id=AUB_1319" or "unknown" for either.--></address>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change type="Transcription" when="2014-01-01" who="spp:"/>
            <!-- Include valid change type: "Transcription," "Revision," or "Publication" with "when=" and valid date" --><change type="Revision" when="2014-01-01" who="spp:"/>
            <change type="Publication" when="2014-01-01" who="spp:"/>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div><!-- Begin Transcription --><p>
            
            [FMS, Auburn, to WHS, Albany, NY, 16 January 1831]<lb/>
               <pb n="1"/>
               <lb/>
            Auburn Sunday evening 16<lb/>
            My Dear Henry, your Thursday’s letter came this morning, it <lb/>
            seems to me my letters are forever getting to you, you have not<lb/>
            received my second yet. I have the vapours most wretchedly. The <lb/>
            destroying angel still continues to visit the dwellings of our neigh-<lb/>
            bours, and why shall we escape? Ambrose Cock<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Cock, Ambrose. (17790813-18500214). 
                  
               </hi> lost another child<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Cock, Solomon Veil. (1830-1831). 
                  
               </hi>
               <lb/>
            on Friday with the scarlet fever, the youngest, about nine months <lb/>
            old. Daniels<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Cock, Daniel Frost. (18061111-18501028).
                  
               </hi> babe<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Cock, Charles Henry. (18291217-18310117). 
                  
               </hi> was alive the last we heard but supposed to be <lb/>
            dying. Mrs. Gunn<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Gunn, Mrs.
                  
               </hi> was buried on Friday the day after her<lb/>
            disease, what a barbarous custom this is of hurrying people under<lb/>
            ground the moment they have ceased to breathe. Catharine 	<lb/>
            M<hi rendition="superscript">c</hi>Donald<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      McDonald, Catherine.
                  
               </hi> spent the day with us yesterday, is still here, nothing<lb/>
            occurred by way of excitement except the chimney’s getting on <lb/>
            fire in the afternoon the remainder of the day Grandma<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      PTM.
                  
               </hi> and<lb/>
            Peter<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Peter.
                  
               </hi> spent in examining the roof of the house to see that it had <lb/>
            not taken fire. Augustus<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      AHS.
                  
               </hi> too was very useful in that way, last <lb/>
            night it had snowed sufficient to make tolerable sleighing, so unpleasant <lb/>
            to day no one ventured out to Church. Teusday morning. I <lb/>
            had written so far sunday night when, while putting the children <lb/>
            in bed I hit my elbow against the bed post, I never had any<lb/>
            thing so trifling occasion so much pain. I think it must have<lb/>
            struck a nerve the chords became contracted and the veins very<lb/>
            much swollen instantly, it continued to pain me until<lb/>
            I went to bed, my wrist was so weak I could not write <lb/>
            any more that evening. I still feel the weakness when I write<lb/>
            but do not apprehend any other ill effects from the blow. Catherine<lb/>
            McDonald is still with us. She is a singular being but with all her<lb/>
            oddities has much good sense and quickness of apprehension. She is older than myself and can reccollect the rise and <lb/>
               <pb n="2"/>
               <lb/>
            progress of the <hi rendition="underline">junto family</hi> as Mrs. G. B. Throop<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Throop, Frances Hunt. (1806-1872). 
                  
                  
                      Throop, George Bliss. (17930412-18540223). 
                  
               </hi> very sapiently<lb/>
            designates them. She has related to me many very amusing <lb/>
            anecdotes about them. I have wandered strangely since I commenced <lb/>
            this letter you must not imagine yours was less interesting to me<lb/>
            because I have said so little about it. I had the hypo when I <lb/>
            commenced writing Sunday evening and felt rather disposed to <lb/>
            quarrel with the post masters because I could not enjoy your <lb/>
            simpathy sooner. The sunshine of monday morning morning displaced<lb/>
            some of these feelings, but my apprehensions about the scarlet fever<lb/>
            still continue. Daniel Cock and his wife<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Cock, Jane Merritt. (18100427-18840326). 
                  
               </hi> have just gone to bury<lb/>
            their babe it died yesterday morning. Dr. Pitney<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Pitney, Dr. Joseph T. (1787-18530420)
                  
               </hi> who like Augustus <lb/>
            thinks one remedy may be effectively applied to all diseases in-<lb/>
            creased the pain of the little sufferer by making an incision<lb/>
            in its throat, because he chanced to be successful when he operated<lb/>
            upon Mr Mills<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Mills. 
                  
               </hi> little girl<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Mills. 
                  
               </hi>, who had the croup. He did the same <lb/>
            to  Dr Vaneps<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Vaneps, Dr. 
                  
               </hi> child<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Vaneps.
                  
               </hi> it died and Vaneps now thinks had he <lb/>
            followed his own judgement the child might have been living.<lb/>
            I would give the world there was one phisician in whom I <hi rendition="strikethrough">had</hi> 
               <lb/>
            might have half the confidence I had in poor Dr. Tuttle<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Tuttle, Dr. Erastus Darwin. (17911216-18290622). 
                  
               </hi>. But <lb/>
            the best phisician cannot always cure. After all the lives of our <lb/>
            babes are in the hands of Him who gave them, of Him who sees<lb/>
            
               <hi rendition="underline">not</hi> as man sees. It gratifies me to know that you think you<lb/>
            would be more happy were I with you but it cannot be. It would<lb/>
            be almost cruel to take my little ones away from a home where they<lb/>
            are so comfortable and happy this cold cold winter. I am <lb/>
            too foolish a mother to leave them, so it cannot be. I think<lb/>
            you will feel less lonely when you become more accustomed to your <lb/>
            new mode of spending your time. Thurlow Weed<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      TxW.
                  
               </hi> I like because <lb/>
            he likes you. Andrews<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Andrews, Samuel George. (17961016-18630611). 
                  
               </hi> I do not like neither do I like his wife<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Andrews, Ann Floyd. ( -18390414). 
                  
               </hi>
               <lb/>
            you could discover no point in her character because there is <lb/>
            none, none that is amiable. When she was 14 years old her<lb/>
               <pb n="3"/>
               <lb/>
            most predominant traits were selfishness and vanity. Maynard<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Maynard, William Hale. (17861123-18320828).
                  
               </hi>
               <lb/>
            could not win a womans heart. But Tracy<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      AHT. 
                  
               </hi>, with his “genius” <lb/>
            his “acquirements,” his “eloquence” and “honorable principles” his fascinating<lb/>
            address and his <hi rendition="underline">ambition</hi> has he a heart. You appear to<lb/>
            have forgotten this in the calender of his virtues. Perhaps a<lb/>
            brilliant imagination occupies the place of one. Mrs Tracy<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Tracy, Harriet Foote Norton. (1800-post1870). 
                  
               </hi> 
               <lb/>
            as you draw her I should esteem but where there is a lady<lb/>
            in the case I had rather trust my own judgement.<lb/>
            Dont think me cynical, you know I <hi rendition="underline">can</hi> and <hi rendition="underline">do</hi> love, <lb/>
            too much for my own happiness some times. The stove does make<lb/>
            the big room very warm. Gus has had no rides with his Grandpa<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      ExM.
                  
               </hi>
               <lb/>
            yet, but promises in profusion. Grandma says Fred<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      FWS.
                  
               </hi> has <hi rendition="underline">grown</hi>
               <lb/>
            to be very nice since he came here to live, but he will never <lb/>
            equal Augustus, with Grandma and Clary<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      CMM.
                  
               </hi>, dear tired he sits<lb/>
            alone and plays on the carpet and looks very meek and nice in<lb/>
            his mother’s eyes [ripped] Augustus is devising all manner of ways to<lb/>
            keep him from Mr Tracy. I cannot persuade him that he will not be<lb/>
            taken perforce. I can tell you to which of the classes of members you do<lb/>
            
               <hi rendition="underline">not</hi> belong. Not to John C. Spencers<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Spencers, John C. (17880108-18550517).
                  
               </hi>, not to Enos’<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Throop, Enos Thompson. (08211784-11011874).
                  
               </hi> I am quite sure. Not<lb/>
            to those who dress, dine, make calls and motions prettily nor to the<lb/>
            mulititude of cyphers I am very positive. If you do not belong to the <lb/>
            other class which is the only one that finds any favour in my eyes<lb/>
            I think you must be a distinct species. It snows again to <lb/>
            day and continues yet, our thermometer has varied very <lb/>
            little during the last week. Saw no one yesterday but Beardsley<hi rendition="endnote_reference">
                  
                      Possibly Beardsley, Nelson. (18080530-18940115).
                  
               </hi>
               <lb/>
            who came for the little tin trunk, did not appear much inclined<lb/>
            to talk, as a specimen of my carefulness, when he went away I looked<lb/>
            for the key but Peter who was standing by said he saw Beardsley put<lb/>
            it in his pocket. I gave up the <hi rendition="strikethrough">seach</hi> search very composedly. This<lb/>
            morning the key was found on the carpet, woe unto me if Pa<lb/>
            had discovered it first. Tomorrow I shall expect the Sunday letter. Your own <lb/>
            Frances<lb/>
               <pb n="4"/>
               <lb/>
            William H. Seward<lb/>
            Albany. <lb/>
            Auburn NY JAN 20<lb/>
            Frances A. Seward 21 Jan. 1831<lb/>
            [alc]<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
